Records of the Finance and Private Sector Development Vice Presidency
World Bank Group Archives
Records of the Finance and Private Sector Development Vice Presidency
1993 - 1997
WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_102
3.89 linear feet of textual records
World Bank Group Archives
Finance and Private Sector Development Vice Presidency
The Finance and Private Sector Development Vice Presidency (FPD) was one of three Vice Presidencies created during President Lewis Preston's reorganization of January 1, 1993. Following the abolishment of all Senior Vice Presidencies on December 1, 1991, Preston initiated a larger reorganization in 1993 that aligned the Bank's organization with the priority areas of its poverty reduction effort. The result was three new thematic vice presidencies: FPD; Human Resources Development and Operations Policy (HRO); and Environmentally Sustainable Development (ESD). The vice presidencies were responsible for:
* providing operational support to the Regions by participating in Sector Operations Division (SOD) task teams, undertaking specialized assignments for the Regions, providing ad hoc advice, distilling lessons of operational experience, disseminating best practices, and defining sector and operational policies
* assisting in identifying and addressing the Bank's skills mix and training needs
* providing information and intellectual support to interested parties outside the Bank
* liaising with the UN and other official and private organizations; and
* delivering complete products to the country directors in the 'clustered' subsectors, where the small number of expert staff can most efficiently be located in the central Vice Presidency.
At the time of its establishment, the FPD Vice Presidency had three departments: the Financial Sector Development Department (FSD); the Private Sector Development Department (PSD); and the Industry and Energy Department (IEN). FSD absorbed the functions and staff of the former Financial Policy and Systems Division of the Country Economics Department (CECFP) located in the Development Economics Vice Presidency (DEC). The PSD absorbed the functions and staff of the former Public Sector Management and Private Sector Development Division of the Country Economics Department (CECPS), which was also previously located in DEC. IEN was transferred from the Sector and Operations PolicyVice Presidency (OPS). FPD departments were responsible for the following functions:
* preparing policies, guidelines, standards, handbooks and analytical tools relevant to the sector
* identifying, codifying and disseminating best practices and lessons of experience, and evaluating weaknesses
* providing advice to the Regions as needed
* monitoring and tracking work in the sectors assigned in order to identify generic issues and identify, evaluate and influence trends and patterns
* performing surveys of experience and practice within the Bank and elsewhere, and developing innovative approaches
* participating in Bankwide efforts to assess skill requirements, and to upgrade skills through recruitment, training, orientation, seminars, newsletters, etc.
* representing the Bank to external communities of interest; and
* maintaining an awareness of relevant external practices and viewpoints.
Jean-Francois Rischard assumed the role as Vice President for FPD in January 1993.
As part of the reorganization of the Bank in 1997, the FPDVP was terminated and replaced with the Finance, Private Sector Development and Infrastructure Network (FPSI). FPSI was created along with three other networks: the Poverty Reduction and Economic Management Network (PREM); the Human Development Network (HDN); and the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Network (ESSD). The FSD, PSD, and IEN departments of FPDVP were transferred to FPSI, joining the new Transportation, Water, and Urban Development Department (TWU).
Published
The fonds consists of budget, work program, planning, management, and organization records related to FPD and its subordinate departments of PSD, FSD, and IEN.
Records were transferred to the World Bank Group Archives using approved records retention and disposition schedules assigned to FPDVP or a Bank-wide schedule for common records.
Accruals are not expected.
* Records of Financial Sector Development Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_99](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-financial-sector-development-sector)).
* Records of Private Sector Development Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_100](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-private-sector-development-sector)).
* Records of the Energy Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA ENGY](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-energy-development-sector)).
* Records of the Industry and Mining Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA IND])(https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-industry-development-sector)).
* Records of the Finance, Private Sector Development, and Infrastructure Network ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_103](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-finance-private-sector-development-and-infrastructure-network)).
* Records of the Private Sector Development Vice Presidency ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_108](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-private-sector-development-vice-presidency)).
* Records of the Private Sector Development and Infrastructure Vice Presidency ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_107](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-private-sector-development-and-infrastructure-vice-presidency)).
* Records of the Sector Policy and Research Vice Presidency (PREVP) and the Sector and Operations Policy Vice Presidency (OSPVP) ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_93](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-sector-policy-and-research-vice-presidency-prevp-and-sector-and-operations-policy-vice-presidency-ospvp)).
* Records related to the Resource Mobilization ([WB IBRD/IDA CFOP](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/resource-mobilization)).
* For records of FPD Vice President Jean-Francois Rischard, see Records of Individual Staff Members - Jean-Francois Rischard files - Vice President, Finance and Private Sector Development Vice Presidency (FPD) chronological files ([WB IBRD/IDA STAFF-28-04](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/vice-president-finance-and-private-sector-development-vice-presidency-fpd-chronological-correspondence-files)).
* See oral history of former FPD and FPSI Vice President [Jean-Francois Rischard](http://oralhistory.worldbank.org/person/rischard-jean-francois).
Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
- FPD budget, business plan, and work program records, 1993-1997; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_102-01; 3.89 linear feet of textual records
  Published
  The series includes budget, business plan, and work program records. The bulk of the records are Private Sector Development Department (PSD) budget records detailing funding for PSD related units for fiscal year 1996. The budget records include: correspondence; memoranda; trust fund letters of representation; budget reports and charts; and travel expense reports. Budget records related to PSD resource mobilization and funding units of the Private Sector Financial Operations Group (CFSPS) and its successor the Private Sector Development and Privatization Group (PSDPS) are also included for the fiscal year 1996. Budget and work program records for FPD involvement with the Consultative Group to Assist the Poor (CGAP) program are included for fiscal years 1995 and 1996. CGAP records include: correspondence; memoranda; budget reports and charts; progress reports; staff and consultant hiring records; and travel expense reports. Records related to the overall planning, management, and organization of FPD and its subordinate departments are also included for fiscal years 1994 to 1996. These records include: correspondence and memoranda between FPD Vice President Jean Francois Rischard and the directors and staff from each department; quarterly, mid-year, and retrospective review reports; staff lists; trust fund budget reports; FPD themes and prospects reports; business plans; and work programs.
  Arranged by subject.
  Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
  - Work Program - Fiscal Year 1994, 1993-09-24 - 1993-12-13; 30221536
  - CFSPS Budget - Trust Fund TF022776 - BB PTF Working File - Fiscal Year 1996 - Volume 1, 1996-04-29 - 1996-06-30; 30221542
  - PSDPS Budget - Year End Print Outs - BB and PTF - Fiscal Year 1996 - Volume 1, 1996-06-01 - 1996-06-30; 30221541
  - Budget 3 - Fiscal Year 1996 - Volume 2, 1996-03-01 - 1996-05-03; 30221576
  - PSD - BTO - West Africa High Level Policy Forum by Anne Marie Chidzaro, 1997-04-10 - 1998-07-18; 30221579
  - CGAP - Budget and Work Program 2 - Fiscal Year 1996, 1996-04-19 - 1996-06-30; 30221577
  - Original Budget and Work Program - Fiscal Year 1996 - Volume 1, 1995-08-01 - 1995-08-30; 30221533
  - Work Program 3 - Fiscal Year 1996 - Volume 1, 1996-04-11 - 1996-06-18; 30221523
  - CGAP - Budget and Work Program - Fiscal Year 1995 / 1996 - Volume 1, 1995-06-13 - 1995-12-20; 30221455
  - Work Program - Correspondence, Working Files, Business Plan, Fiscal Year 1994 Retrospective Review - Fiscal Year 1995 - Volume 1, 1994-05-14 - 1994-09-11; 30221537
  - Work Program - Fiscal Year 1995 Retrospective Review, Fiscal Year 1996 Quarterly Review, Fiscal Year 1996 Business Plan, Themes, Prospects (FPD), Mid Year - Fiscal Year 1996 - Volume 1, 1996-02-01 - 1996-02-28; 30221535
  - CFSPS - CAM - Fiscal Year 1996, 1996-01-03 - 1996-12-08; 30221578
  - Budget 3 - Fiscal Year 1996 - Volume 1, 1996-05-21 - 1996-06-07; 30221575
  - CFSPS Budget - Print Outs - Fiscal Year 1996, 1996-01-11 - 1996-06-10; 30221607
  - Budget 1 - Fiscal Year 1996, 1995-07-12 - 1995-08-03; 30221617
  - Budget 2 - Fiscal Year 1996, 1996-02-15 - 1996-03-25; 30221616
  - Budget 4 - Fiscal Year 1996, 1996-04-11 - 1996-07-17; 30221613
  - PSD - Trust Fund TF023965 - Governance and Successful Adjustment - Background Material - Yunshin Byrne - Volume 1, 1993-03-11 - 1994-12-14; 30221640